<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lieu. Col. John Lilburn's plea in law, against an Act of Parliament of the 30 of January, 1651. entituled, An act for the execution of a judgment given in Parliament against Lieu. Col. John Lilburn. Contrived and penned, on purpose for him, by a true and faithful lover of the fundamental laws and liberties of the free people of England, ... all which compels and forceth the penman to be very studious of his own good and preservation, ... and therefore, for his own good and benefit, the honest readers information, and for Mr Lilburns the prisoners advantage, he presents these ensuing lines to thy view, and his, as the form of a plea; that the penman hereof, as a true well-wisher of his, and the people of England, would have him to ingross into parchment, and to have ready by him to make use of (in case his own braines cannot contrive a better) when he is called up to answer for his life before the judges of the upper-bench, or any other bar of justice whatsoever; and the said form of a plea for him thus followeth verbatim.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_12*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862932</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E703[12*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lieu. Col. John Lilburn's plea in law, against an Act of Parliament of the 30 of January, 1651. entituled, An act for the execution of a judgment given in Parliament against Lieu. Col. John Lilburn. Contrived and penned, on purpose for him, by a true and faithful lover of the fundamental laws and liberties of the free people of England, ... all which compels and forceth the penman to be very studious of his own good and preservation, ... and therefore, for his own good and benefit, the honest readers information, and for Mr Lilburns the prisoners advantage, he presents these ensuing lines to thy view, and his, as the form of a plea; that the penman hereof, as a true well-wisher of his, and the people of England, would have him to ingross into parchment, and to have ready by him to make use of (in case his own braines cannot contrive a better) when he is called up to answer for his life before the judges of the upper-bench, or any other bar of justice whatsoever; and the said form of a plea for him thus followeth verbatim.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition much inlarged, corrected, and amended, July 2. 1653.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Lilburn himself.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>The Act was passed in 1652.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Lieu. Col. John Lilburn's Plea in Law, Againſt an Act of Parliament of the 30 of January, 1651. Entituled, <hi>An Act for the execution of</hi> a Judgment <hi>given in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt Lieu. Col.</hi> John Lilburn. Contrived and penned, on purpoſe for him, by a true and faithful lover of the Fundamental Laws and Liberties of the free people of <hi>England,</hi> a great deal more then of the perſon of Lieu. col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> though now he be a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for the ſaid Lawes, and Liberties, and his own innocency, in Newgate: All which compels and forceth the Penman to be very ſtudious of his own good and preſervation, very much concerned, and very much incroached upon, in that harſh, unjuſt, and illegal dealing, that at preſent is exerciſed upon him: And therefore, for his own good and benefit, the honeſt Readers information, and for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lilburns</hi> the priſoners advantage, he preſents theſe enſuing lines to thy view, and his, as the form of a <hi>Plea;</hi> that the Penman here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as a true well-wiſher of his, and the people of <hi>England,</hi> would have him to ingroſs into Parchment, and to have ready by him to make uſe of (in caſe his own braines cannot contrive a better) when he is called up to anſwer for his life before the Judges of the Upper-Bench, or any other Bar of Juſtice whatſoever; and the ſaid form of a Plea for him thus followeth verbatim.</head>
            <head type="sub">The ſecond Edition much inlarged, corrected, and amended, <hi>July 2. 1653.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the Bar ſaith, that he having heard the Charge contained in the <hi>Scire facias, Indictment,</hi> or <hi>Information,</hi> now read unto him at the Bar: For plea thereunto he ſaith, That it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the Act of Parl of the 30 of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. That upon the 15. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. a Judgment was given in Parl. againſt one Lieu. Col. <hi>Jo. Lilburn,</hi> in the Act named, for <hi>high crimes and miſdemeanors by him committed,</hi> as by the ſame appeares, for which the fines and other puniſhments were promulgated againſt him, mentioned in the ſaid Act. But the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn now priſoner</hi> at the Bar ſaith, <hi>that the ſaid J. Lilburn in the ſaid Act named,</hi> and he the now <hi>priſoner</hi> at the Bar, be not one and the ſelf-ſame perſon; for that he the now <hi>priſoner</hi> at the Bar is a free-born Engliſh Gentleman; <hi>and never was legally charged, indicted, &amp; convicted,</hi> either by the Parl. or any other Court of Judicature, <hi>being a Court of Record,</hi> in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166601:2"/>
the Engliſh Nation, or Commonwealth: Neither ever was there any Judgment given in Parl. againſt him the now <hi>priſoner</hi> at the Bar, <hi>for high crimes and miſdemeanors mentioned in the ſaid Act,</hi> upon the ſaid 15 of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651 <hi>(Votes or Reſolves being not in the leaſt any judgments in law)</hi> It <hi>being</hi> impoſſible that a Judgment in any legal Court of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be paſt againſt a free-born Engliſh man; and that man dayly forth-coming, and never to hear read, nor ſee any of the proceedings ante-ceding the ſaid Judgment, and never ſummoned by any legal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to any legal proceedings, nor called to any legal Bar whatſoever, and demanded (according to Law) what he could ſay, why Judgment ſhould not be paſt againſt him. Neither ever did the <hi>priſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner J. Lilburn,</hi> now at the Bar, ever in all his life-time, by kneeling at the Bar of the P. of the Commonwelth of <hi>England,</hi> lately ſitting at <hi>Weſtm.</hi> ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the ſaid Parl. in law, ever had in all their life times, any the leaſt juriſdiction in the world, <hi>to ſentence him, or any other free-born Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man of England,</hi> (that are none of their Members of immedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers) <hi>for any crimes whatſoever,</hi> as <hi>I. Lilburn</hi> the priſoner at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bar hath fully and undeniably proved by Law in his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea (upon the Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi>) before the late Judges of the Kings Bench, <hi>viz.</hi> Judge <hi>Bacon,</hi> and Judge <hi>Rolls,</hi> upon the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1648. as in that printed Law-Argument, entituled, <hi>The lawes funeral,</hi> is fully to be read in pag. 8 9, 10, 11. All <hi>crimes</hi> whatſoever being for him, onely and ſolely to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard, determined, and judged at the Common-law, and no where elſe. For, Magna Charta th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tition of Right, and the Act that aboliſhed the Star-Chamber, expreſly ſaith, <hi>That no free-man of England ſhall be taken, or impriſoned, or be diſſeized of his free hold, or liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or free cuſtomes, or be out-lawed or be ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led, but by a lawful Judgment</hi> (of a Jury of 12 ſworn men) of <hi>his equals</hi> (of the ſame neighborhood) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of the Land. And that none ſhalbe taken</hi> (for any crime whatſoever, by any perſon or Court whatſoever) <hi>unleſs it be by indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or preſentment of good and lawful people of the ſame neighborhood where ſuch deeds be done, in due manner, or by proceſs made by Writ original at the Common law, and that none be put out of his franchiſe or free-hold, unleſs he be duly brought in to anſwer and adjudged of the ſame according to the courſe of the Law, and if any thing be done</hi> (by any perſons, or Courts wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoever) <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tenor of the ſame it ſhall be void in Law, and holden for error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Petition of Right expreſly ſaith, <hi>No man whatſoever ſhall be any wayes puniſhed</hi> (eſpecially in criminal caſes) <hi>but according to the Laws and Statutes already eſtabliſhed in the Land.</hi> And thoſe alſo by the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Right, and the Statute that aboliſhed the Star-Chamber, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166601:2"/>
preciſely declared to be according to our <hi>good, old, native, fundamental Rights &amp; Liberties.</hi> This very thing (or the ſecuring therof) alone, being the principal and chief declared cauſe of all the late Parl. and preſent Armies wars with the late King and his ſon; and without the invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable preſervation of theſe our fundamental laws and liberties, it is impoſſible that any in the Army, from the higheſt to the loweſt, in the leaſt can acquit themſelves of being juſtly eſteemed, both before God and all juſt men, real and wilful murderers, of all thoſe perſons that they have ſlain in the late civil wars; and if ſo? woe unto them when God makes inquiſition for innocent bloud. Neither indeed, is he the now <hi>priſoner</hi> at the Bar, guilty of any ſuch high crimes and miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, as is expreſſed in the ſaid Act: Neither ever was he the now <hi>priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> at the Bar, <hi>in the leaſt duly and legally baniſhed, and fined by the ſaid Act; nor yet is a fellon, nor guilty of fellony</hi> in no manner of reſpect, as by the ſaid <hi>Scire facias, Indictment,</hi> or <hi>Information,</hi> now read unto him is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: Neither can he rationally imagine, that by the Parl. that is mentioned in the ſaid Act of the 30 of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. for baniſhing one Lieu. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> is not in the leaſt meant the late Parl. of the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (eſpecially, becauſe it is not ſo expreſt) who had taken many Oaths, and paſt abundance of Declarations, and particularly that of the 9 of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1648. inviolably <hi>to maintain the funda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ental Lawes of the Land, in reference to the peoples lives, liberties, and properties, with all things incident, appertainining, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto;</hi> But that rather it was ſome ignorant ſottiſh French Parl. ſitting at <hi>Paris,</hi> or elſewhere in <hi>France, that underſtand nothing of the laws, liberties, and freedomes of England,</hi> or that it was the <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Cavalier Parl.</hi> lately ſitting at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the Kings <hi>Quarters</hi> there, <hi>poſt-dating their Act,</hi> and thereby endeavoring by the ſaid Act, to create ſuch a a preſident as in the conſequence of it <hi>would deſtroy all the lawes, liberties, and properties, of the free-born people of England,</hi> and thereby ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſet up the Kings Will and Prerogative above Law, the bare endeavouring of which in the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> hath bin long ſince ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgd high Treaſon. Or in the next place, if the Authors of the ſaid <hi>monſtrous</hi> and illegal Act of baniſhment, <hi>be neither the ignorant Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Paris,</hi> nor the <hi>Cavalier Parliament of Oxford,</hi> then of neceſſity in the third place, it cannot in Charity and Reaſon but be judged that the ſaid Act of baniſhment was drawn up by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Scobel,</hi> the Parliaments Clerk, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hill</hi> their Chairman, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Prideaux</hi> their Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, when they were all riding Poſt, and ſo jumbled or ſhaken with faſt riding, that it was impoſſible for them to hold their pens to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166601:3"/>
write right and true; and when they had framed it, <hi>then by ſome cunning artifice, or inchantment of theirs,</hi> they preferred it to the ſaid Parl. who in charity and common Reaſon muſt needs be <hi>judged to paſs it when they were three quarters aſleep,</hi> againſt ſome ſillie natural fool called Lieu. col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> that could not be imagined ever in his life to have read any thing of Law or Reaſon. It being impoſſible (in the leaſt) in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be conceived, <hi>that the late ſupream Authority the Parl. of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of England ſitting at Weſtminſter,</hi> being onely by their own Declarations, but truſted to provide <hi>for the Peoples weal, but not in the least for their woe,</hi> would ever in their right wits, or not being three quarters aſleep, paſs ſuch an Act of Parliament againſt <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the Bar (<hi>who hath much read the law, and very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the fundamental liberties of England,</hi> and hath hazardouſly adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured his life a thouſand times for the inviolable preſerving of them) becauſe ſuch an Act of Parl. as the foreſaid Act of Parl. is, is in the firſt place, <hi>An Act of Parliament againſt common right, common equity, &amp; common reaſon;</hi> and therfore is void and null in law, and ought not to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as appears by theſe following Law Authorities, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 part of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bonhams</hi> Caſe, <hi>fol.</hi> 118. and the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 3. 30. 33 <hi>E.</hi> caſſavit 32. and 27 <hi>H. G.</hi> annuity 41. and 1 <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 113. and 1 part Cooks Inſtitutes, lib. 2. chap. 11. ſect. 209. <hi>fol.</hi> 140. <hi>a.</hi> 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. 12. 12 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. 18. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 12. 13. <hi>Plow. com. fol.</hi> 369. and Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> learned Works in the Law, printed for <hi>I. Gyles,</hi> 1648. but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by his Diſcourſe of long Parliaments, <hi>pag.</hi> 139, 140, &amp;c. See alſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>W. Prins</hi> notable book of the 16 of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1649. called, <hi>A legal Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the liberties of England againſt illegal taxes, p.</hi> 11, 12, 13. &amp;c. But eſpecially ſee a book, entituled, <hi>The legal and fundamental liberties of England revived, aſſerted, and vindicated; printed and reprinted in the year,</hi> 1649. <hi>pag.</hi> 54, 55, 56, 57. yea an Act of Parl. <hi>That a man ſhall be Judges in his own Caſe, is avoid Act in law;</hi> as appeares in <hi>Hubberts</hi> Caſe, <hi>fol.</hi> 120. and by the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Part of <hi>Cookes</hi> Reports in D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bonhams</hi> Caſe, and by <hi>the preſent Armies own Book of Declarations, pag.</hi> 35, 52, 54, 59, 60, 61, 63, 132, 141, 142, 143, 144. Yea, ſaith that learned Oracle of the Law of <hi>England</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edw. Cook,</hi> in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of his Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 330. <hi>Where Reaſon ceaſeth, there the Law ceaſeth; for, ſeeing Reaſon is the very life and ſpirit of the law it ſelf, the law-giver is not to be eſteemed, to reſpect that which hath no Reaſon; although the generality of the words, at the firſt ſight, or after the letter, ſeem otherwiſe.</hi> And ſaith the ſaid learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in his firſt part Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 140. <hi>a. All Cuſtoms and preſcriptions (Acts of Parliament, Lawes and Iudgments) that be againſt Reaſon, are void and null in themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166601:3"/>And ſaith the Armies Atturny General <hi>John Cook,</hi> in the late Kings Caſe ſtated, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. that by the law of England, any Act or agreement againſt the laws of God and nature, is a meer nullity: for as a man hath no hand in making the laws of God and nature, no more hath he power to marre or alter them; and he cites the E. of Leiceſters ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged Caſe for a proof: And in <hi>pag.</hi> the 20t<hi rend="sup">h</hi> he alſo ſaith, <hi>That all the Judges in England cannot make one caſe to be law that is not reaſon, no more then they can prove a hair to be white that is black;</hi> which if they ſhould ſo declare or adjudge it is a meer nullity; <hi>For law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>must be reaſon adjudged.</hi> And excellent to this very purpoſe, is that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Law Book, called <hi>the Doctor and Student,</hi> who in his ſecond <hi>Chap. pag.</hi> 4. expreſly ſaith, <hi>Against the law of Nature</hi> (which he cals the law of reaſon) <hi>preſcription, ſtatute, nor cuſtome, may not prevail; and if any be brought in againſt it, they be no preſcriptions, ſtatutes, nor cuſtoms, but things void and against juſtice;</hi> And what this law of nature or reaſon is, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently ſheweth in the latter end of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>pag.</hi> and the beginning of the fifth; and therefore in his 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>pag.</hi> he expreſly ſaith, <hi>That to every good law, is required theſe properties,</hi> viz. <hi>that it be honest, rightwiſe, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in it ſelf, and after the cuſtom of the country, convenient for the place and time; neceſſary, profitable, and alſo manifest; that it be not captious by any dark ſentence, nor mixt with any private wealth, but all made for the common good; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>every mans law muſt be conſonant to the law of God, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are not righteous, nor obligatory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch an Act of Parliament as the foreſaid Act of Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is not onely againſt common-right, common-equity, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-reaſon; <hi>but it is abſolutely deſtructive to the very ends of the peoples truſt conferred upon the Parliament;</hi> and ſo the higheſt of Treaſons that can be committed, and that it is deſtructive to the ends of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Truſts, clearly appears by the Statutes of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, chap. 14. and 36 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 10. which expreſly ſaith, That a <hi>Parliament at leaſt ſhall be holden once every year; and that for the maintenance of the Peoples lawes and liberties, and the redreſs of divers miſchiefs and grievances that dayly happen;</hi> and ſuitable to theſe things, are the ends contained in the Writs that ſummon them, &amp; the intentions of thoſe that chuſe the Members and ſend them. And ſuitable to this is the ends of Parl. ſitting, as the preſent General and his Army in many of their remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Declarations have fully declared againſt the late 11 members, &amp; their Accomplices: Yea, and forced the late Parl. to raze out of their Books and Records, many wicked and unrighteous things, as they judged them to be, after the Parl. had ſolemnly paſt them; as Votes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166601:4"/>
Orders, Iudgments, and Acts; yea, and endeavoured very earneſtly to hang divers of thoſe as Traytors that had executed them; as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, Alderman <hi>Adams, Langham,</hi> and <hi>Bunch;</hi> with the Lord Major S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Gayer,</hi> &amp;c. But the greateſt grievances and miſchiefs in the world are by the foreſaid miſchievous and unjuſt baniſhing Act, eſtabliſhed, ratified, and confirmed; for by it a man is condemned to loſe his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and eſtate, and all the comforts of this life; and that without any the <hi>leaſt crime committed, or accuſation exhibited, or legal proceſs iſſued out to ſummon the party to make any defence in the world, or ever calling or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to ſpeak one word for himſelf;</hi> Which is an act or proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light and law of <hi>Nature, Reaſon, the Law of God, againſt the Law of Honour, Conſcience, and common-honeſty;</hi> yea, a dealing worſe with the party, then ever the cruel Jewes did with Chriſt; or, then the bloudy Butchers, Biſhop <hi>Gardiner</hi> and <hi>Bonner</hi> did with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaſted Martyrs in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> dayes; <hi>who alwayes ſuffered them to have due proceſs of law, and to know and ſee their Accuſers, and to have free liberty to ſpeak for themſelves;</hi> and never condemned them, but for tranſgreſſing a known and declared Law in being.</p>
            <p>Yea alſo dealing worſe with the party then ever the bloudy Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Traitors were dealt with by King <hi>James,</hi> who always allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them fair trials in law, from the beginning to the end, at the Bar of Juſtice, for their lives: Yea it is a worſe dealing with the party, then ever the Parliament themſelves dealt with the bloudieſt and moſt maſſacring traitors that ever was in arms againſt them to cut their throats. Yea, the fore-mentioned practice, of the foreſaid moſt ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and unrighteous Act of baniſhment, is an Act, and proceedings in the higheſt ſubverſion of the fundamental law and liberty of <hi>England,</hi> that can be invented or imagined; and by conſequence, if it may without the higheſt offence, or ſoliciſmes in Law be ſuppoſed, that his Excellency the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> and the reſt of the Members of the late ſupream Authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> ſitting at <hi>Westminster,</hi> had any real finger in it, or were Actors of it, they may and ought all of them, with all the reſt under them, that have executed any part of the foreſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, injurious, illegal Act of Parliament, be <hi>apprehended, indicted, and proceſſed againſt at the common-law, as Traytors, and ſubverters of the fundamental lawes, liberties, and freedoms, of the free-born people of</hi> England: As that learned man in the Lawes of England, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> in the ſecond, third, and fourth parts of his Inſtitutes (all three of which are publiſhed by two ſpecial Orders of the late Houſe of Commons, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166601:4"/>
               <hi>Anno,</hi> 1641. for good Law) doth declare, and proof was dealt with by <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> in leſſe Caſes, then the before recited unjuſt Act of baniſhment. Which Caſe of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> was thus:</p>
            <p>At the Parliament holden by King, Lords, and Commons, in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſevenths time, who was a moſt undoubted lawful King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and by his Marriage of his Wife the Lady <hi>Elizabeth, Heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Houſe of York,</hi> as Himſelf was to the Houſe of Lancaſter, had united the two claims of Lancaſter and York in Himſelf; and in pitcht-battel had ſlain King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, the Uſurper; and by reaſon of the extraordinary many troubles of His Reign, and the ignorant Regal time in which he lived conſidered, He had a thouſand times more grounds to be arbytrary and diſcretionary in his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the people of England, then the late <hi>decapitated</hi> Parliament had. Yet he ſummoned a <hi>free Parliament,</hi> who ſate peaceably and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, without the force <hi>or purgings of ſoldiers,</hi> and after that ſeveral Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, at Aſſizes and Seſſions by corruption and favour, had refuſed to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de perſons that were judicially proved guilty before them of br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach of penal laws, as in full and free Parliament <hi>by King, Lords and Commons,</hi> is avowedly declared; An Act of Parliament (<hi>recorded in the</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>part of Cooks Inſtitutes, fol.</hi> 40, 41.) <hi>in the</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 3 <hi>was paſt by King, Lords and Commons,</hi> in full and free parliament, to enable the Juſtices of Aſſize in open Seſſions <hi>to be holden before them, and the Juſtices of peace in each country in England, upon information for the King before them to be made, to have full power and authority by their diſcretion</hi> (with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut trials by Juries) <hi>to hear and determine all offences and contempts committed against penal laws:</hi> In all which arbitrary or diſcretion I proceedings, <hi>murther, treaſon and felony, was excepted out of their</hi> cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance or juriſdiction, <hi>as alſo all other offences whereby any perſon ſhould loſe life, or member, or lands, tenements, goods, or chattels to the party</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining.</p>
            <p>By pretext of which ſtatute ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his laſt recited <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> (privie Counſellors and Juſtices of peace to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh) <hi>did commit upon the ſubject inſufferable preſſures and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions</hi> (which yet at the higheſt was but the taking away ſome ſmall part of the perſons eſtates from them that they condemned) <hi>and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ſtatute was juſtly ſoon after the deceaſe of</hi> Henry <hi>the ſeventh repealed at the next Parliament after his deceaſe,</hi> by <hi>the ſtatute of the</hi> 1 <hi>Hen</hi> 8. <hi>chap</hi> 6. A good caveat ſaith he to parliaments, <hi>to leave all cauſes to be meaſured by the golden and ſtreight wet-wand of the law, and not to the uncertain and crooked cord of diſcretion.</hi> For it is not almoſt credible to fore-ſee (saith
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166601:5"/>
he) <hi>when any maxime, or fundamental law of this Realm is altered</hi> (as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where hath been obſerved) <hi>what dangerous inconveniences do follow, which most expreſly appeareth by this most unjust and ſtrange Act of</hi> 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>For hereby not onely</hi> Empſon <hi>and</hi> Dudley <hi>themſelves, but ſuch Juſtices of peace</hi> (corrupt men) <hi>as they cauſed to be authoriſed, committed most grievous and heavy oppreſſions and exactions, grinding the face of the poor ſubjects by penal laws</hi> (be they never ſo obſolete or unfit for the time) <hi>by information one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without any preſentment or trial by Jury, being the ancient birth-right of the ſubject, but to hear and determine the ſame by</hi> their diſcretion, <hi>inflicting ſuch penalty, as the ſtatutes not repealed impoſed. Theſe and other like actions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions by, or by the means of</hi> Empſon <hi>and</hi> Dudley <hi>and their inſtruments, brought infinite treaſures to the Kings Coffers, whereof the King himſelf in the end, with great grief and compunction repented, as in another place we have obſerved. This ſtatute of</hi> 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>we have recited, and ſhewed the just in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences therof, to the end, that the like ſhould never hereafter be attempted in any Court of Parliament, and that others might avoid the fearful end of thoſe two Time-ſervers</hi> Empſon <hi>and</hi> Dudley. Qui eorum veſtigia inſiſtant, eorum exitus perhorreſcant. That is to ſay, <hi>Thoſe that follow their foot-ſteps, may fear the ſame deſtruction that they had;</hi> whoſe end in the third part of the Inſtitutes fol. 208. and the fourth part fol. 198, 199. may be ſeen; was ſeverally to be <hi>indicted at Common law</hi> (whoſe indictments is there to be read) <hi>and convicted and executed as Traitors,</hi> for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the fundamental Law and Liberties of England, viz. <hi>Trials by Juries:</hi> which the Conqueſts of the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes,</hi> or <hi>Normans,</hi> could never blot out of the Kalendar of Engliſhmens fundamental Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, but hath from time to time, with the infinite hazards of their lives and blouds been preſerved, as the choiſeſt of their jewels, and as one of their chiefeſt fundamental right.</p>
            <p>Of whom the ſaid Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his expoſition of the 29 Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> in his ſecond part, Inſtitutes fol. 51, upon the words of <hi>lex terra,</hi> or the law of the Land (where he plentifully ſhews, that no Engliſhman whatſoever, <hi>ought not for any crime whatſoever, in any Court whatſoever, by any power or authority whatſoever,</hi> to be tried but by Juries, and due proceſs of Law as is before ſhewed) expreſly ſaith; Yet</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Against this ancient and fundamental Law, and in the face thereof, I finde an Act of Parliament made</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that aſwel Juſtices of Aſſize, as Juſtices of Peace</hi> (without any finding or preſentment by the verdict of twelve men) <hi>upon a bare information for the King before them made, ſhould have full power and authority by</hi> their diſcretions to <hi>hear and determine</hi> all offences <hi>and contempts committed or done by any perſon or perſons, against the form, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166601:5"/>
and effect of any Statute, made and not repealed, &amp;c.</hi> By colour of which Act, ſhaking this fundamental Law, <hi>it is not credible what hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible oppreſſions and exactions, to the undoing infinite numbers of people,</hi> were committed by Sir <hi>Richard Empſon</hi> Knight, and <hi>Edmond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dley,</hi> being Juſtices of the Peace throughout <hi>England,</hi> and upon this unjuſt and injurious Act (as commonly in ſixe caſes it falleth out) a new Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was erected, and they made Maſters of the Kings forfeitures.</p>
            <p>But at the Parliament hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the firſt year of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, this Act of the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>is recited, and made void, and repealed, and the reaſon thereof is yeilded, for that by force of the ſaid Act it was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly known, that many ſiniſter and crafty feigned forged informations, had been perſued against divers of the Kings ſubjects, to their great dammage and wrongfull vexations, and the ill ſucceſs hereof, and the fearful ends of the two Oppreſſors, ſhould deterr others from committing the like,</hi> and ſhould admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Parliaments, <hi>That inſtead of the ordinary and pretious trial</hi> (per legem terra) by the law of the Land, <hi>they bring not in Abſolute, and partial trials by diſcretion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the fourth part of his Inſtitutes fol. 37. he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith, <hi>That he findes an Attainder by Parliament of a ſubject (viz. Thomas Cromwel</hi> then Earl of Eſſex) <hi>of High Treaſon,</hi> who was committed to the Tower, and thereby forth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to be heard, <hi>and yet was never called to anſwer in any of the Houſes of Parliament.</hi> Of the manner of which proceeding he thus ſaith; <hi>Auferat oblivio, ſi potest, ſi non, utcunque ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam tegat;</hi> That is, <hi>Let the Parliaments crime be buried in oblivion, if it be poſſible; and if not, nevertheleſs, yet let it give place to ſilence for the preſent.</hi> For ſaith he, <hi>the more high and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute the juriſdiction of the Court is, the more just and honourable it ought to be in the proceeding, and to give example of Juſtice to inferiour Courts.</hi> And fol. 38. he is confidently perſwaded, that the rehearſal of this <hi>unjust Attainder,</hi> will <hi>hereafter cauſe the Honourable Members</hi> of both Houſes of Parliament, to be ſo tender of their duty, in preſerving the fundamental Lawes and liberties of the people of England, <hi>as that never hereafter ſuch an unjust Attainder ſhall be brought, where the party is forth comming, to condemn him, without hearing of him.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant unto this, is the Scripture and the Law of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166601:6"/>
contained, as appears by the third of <hi>Gen. verſ.</hi> 9. where God after <hi>Adam</hi> had tranſgreſſed his Law, <hi>ſummons him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him to anſwer for himſelf, before he would paſs judgement against him.</hi> And when <hi>Sodom</hi> had abhominably defiled its wayes, with the height of wickedneſs, yet the juſt God of heaven and earth, would not judge, condemn or paſs ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt them, <hi>Till he went down to ſee, whether they have done altogether according to the cry that is come up againſt them, or not;</hi> And ſaith God, <hi>I will know,</hi> Gen. 18. And <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.6.11. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.15. God ſaith expreſly, <hi>One Witneſs ſhall not riſe againſt a man for any iniquity, or for any ſin, in any ſin that he ſinneth; at the mouth of two witneſſes, or at the mouth of three witneſſes, ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed.</hi> And by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> he required the people of Iſrael, <hi>to do according to the ſentence of the Law, &amp; the judgment which ſhall be given there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and not to decline from the law, to the right hand, or to the left.</hi> And ſuitable to this is the judicial and legal proceedings of the great Congregation of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (conſiſting to the number of four hundred thouſand able men) in the caſe of the <hi>Levite,</hi> and his raviſhed and ſlain Concubine, who in their judicial proceedings in that Caſe, <hi>firſt demanded of him, how ſo great a wickednes came to be committed in</hi> Iſrael? <hi>And the concluſion, after their hearing, and examining the cauſe, was to conſider, conſult, and then to give ſentence.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus,</hi> that learned man in the Law of God, againſt the Scribes and Phariſees, in behalf of <hi>Chriſt, Doth our Law judge any man before it hear him?</hi> John 7.51. And ſaith <hi>Feſtus,</hi> the Heathen Roman Governor in Judea (that had no other guide to walk by, but the Light and Law of Nature) in the behalf of <hi>Paul,</hi> againſt his bloudy enemies; <hi>It is not the manner of the Romans to deliver any one to die, before that he which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed have the accuſers face to face, and have licence to anſwer for himſelf,</hi> Act. 25.16. And ſaith righteous <hi>Paul,</hi> who writ the Oracles of God, infallibly by the Spirit of God; <hi>where there is no law, there is, nor can be no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. And as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166601:6"/>
evil ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in the laſt fore-cited <hi>fol.</hi> was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in Parliament, in the ſecond of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. againſt Sir <hi>John Mortimer, the third ſon of Edmund the ſecond E. of</hi> March, (deſcended from <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence) who was indicted of High Treaſon, for certain words; which Indictment</hi> (without any Arraignment or pleading) <hi>being meerly feigned to blemiſh the Title of the</hi> Mortimers; <hi>and withall, being inſufficient in Law, as by the ſame appeareth, was confirmed by Authority of Parliament. And the ſaid</hi> Sir John <hi>being brought into the Parliament, without Arraignment, and Anſwer, Judgment in Parliament was given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, upon the ſaid Indictment, that he ſhould be carryed to the Tower of London, and drawn through the city to Tyburn, and there hanged, drawn, and quartered; his head to be ſet on London Bridge; his four quarters on the four gates of London; as by the Record of Parliament appeareth.</hi> And therefore, in the next <hi>folio,</hi> being <hi>fol.</hi> 39. he ſaith, That whereas by Order of Law, a <hi>man cannot be attainted of high Treaſon, unleſs the Offence be in Law high Treaſon: he ought not to be attainted by general words of high Treaſon, by Authority of Parliament</hi> (as ſomtime hath been uſed) <hi>but the high treaſon ought to be ſpecially expreſſed, ſeeing that the Court of Parliament is the higheſt and moſt honourable Court of Juſtice, and ought</hi> (as hath been ſaid) <hi>to give example to inferior Courts.</hi> And further to ſhew that Parliaments (which in their right conſtitution are the beſt conſervators of our Laws, and Liberties) are erroneous things (when they walk by their own Wills, and forſake their true and only guide <hi>the fanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Lawes of England</hi>) what need there any more inſtances then many of the Armies own Declarations; in ſeverall of which, and their frequent Diſcourſes, they have declared the late parliament a <hi>trayterous Parliament, Breakers of their Truſt,</hi> and embroylers of the Nation in bloudy wars, and <hi>ſubverters of the peoples liberties and freedoms;</hi> yea, and in the concluſion, the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> himſelf, and Maj. Gen. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> with their own hands have pul'd <hi>them</hi> out by the ears, and pluckt them up by the very Roots, <hi>as final breakers of their truſt,</hi> &amp; as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166601:7"/>
a pack of the vildeſt knaves and villaines that ever breathed in <hi>England;</hi> Although <hi>they</hi> were fenced in, and about by an <hi>Act</hi> of parliament made before the wars, by <hi>King, Lords, and Commons, that they ſhould not be diſſolved, but by their own free and voluntary conſents;</hi> And, alſo, ſince they changed the Kingdom into a Commonwealth, by two ſeveral Acts of parl. of the 14 of <hi>May,</hi> 1649. and the 17 of <hi>July,</hi> 1649. in which it is expreſly made high Treaſon, <hi>for any Engliſhman, or men, by writing, printing, or words declaring; or by endeavouring to raiſe or ſtir up Force to diſſolve the late parliamment, or their councel of ſtate, without their own conſents or to ſay, that the ſaid late parl. or their councel of ſtate is tyrannical, uſurped, or unlawful,</hi> as by the ſaid Acts of Parl. with reference thereunto being had, more at large doth appear; (which Acts are printed in the firſt part of the Tryal or Arraignment of the priſoner at the Bar at <hi>Guild-hall, Octob.</hi> 1649. <hi>pag.</hi> 86, 87, 88, 89) And the ſaid <hi>J. Lilburn,</hi> now priſoner at the <hi>Bar,</hi> for further plea ſaith, That for ſuppoſed violating thoſe two laſt forementioned Acts of Parl. and that but for ſuppoſed words, and for the ſuppoſed, compiling, writing, and cauſing to be printed, <hi>Arguments,</hi> founded at grounded upon the known and declared <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Lawes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the received principals of Reaſon, and the Armies own printed and publiſhed Declarations; he the ſaid <hi>Joh. Lilburn,</hi> now priſoner at the Bar, was arraigned, and indicted, as a Traytor for his life at <hi>Guildhall, London,</hi> in <hi>Octo.</hi> 1649. <hi>And that principally by the inſtigation and means of his Excellency the preſent L. G. Cromwel;</hi> which Tryal was with that violence and fury, <hi>that the ſaid priſoner at the Bar</hi> was abſolutely denied the declared benefit of the known <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> viz. <hi>the help of Councel learned in the Law</hi> (and a copy of his Charge and Indictment) which were not denyed, but granted to the Lord <hi>Macquire,</hi> that grand Iriſh Rebel, and thoſe arch Traytors, as they are commonly called, <hi>Strafford, Canterbury, Hambleton, Capel</hi> &amp;c. and which alſo was granted to the priſoner at the Bar, as his <hi>Right by Law,</hi> when he was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166601:7"/>
priſoner at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and arraigned by Judge <hi>Heath,</hi> &amp;c. for his life as a traytor; ſo that the ſaid <hi>J. Lilburn</hi> now priſoner, at the Bar, conſidering the ſeveral <hi>penalties</hi> declared to be due, to <hi>any</hi> perſon, or perſons whatſoever, <hi>that by force or otherwiſe ſhould but indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to diſſolve the late Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. or the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Councel of State,</hi> he cannot either in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Law, ſee or apprehend which way his Excellency the ſaid L.G. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and M. Gen. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> &amp;c. if they continue and perſevere as they have begun, to execute the ſaid unjuſt and injurious Act of parl. upon the ſaid <hi>J. Lilburn,</hi> priſoner at the Bar, (which is one of the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked'ſt, and unjuſt, that ever the Parl. in their lives made, and one of the higheſt and moſt notorious Acts of their breach of truſt that ever they committed; as is before fully proved) can in the leaſt either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God or Man, acquit themſelves of being guilty of the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of Treaſon, both by the letter and equity of the two laſt forementioned Lawes (lately made in part by themſelves; but principally by their inſtigation) in forcibly diſſolving the late parl. againſt their own vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary wills and conſents; or how they can acquit themſelves in the leaſt in the eyes of all the underſtanding people in <hi>England,</hi> to be juſtly eſteemed guilty of plucking up the parl. by the roots, not in the leaſt for any evil oppreſſion, injuſtice, or breach of truſt they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the Nation, or honeſt people thereof (that never yet in the leaſt, upon their own principles, forfeited their <hi>liberties</hi> &amp; <hi>freedoms</hi>) but onely becauſe they would deſtroy the parl. to have the power in their own hands; thereby to diſpoſe of all the <hi>lives, liberties,</hi> and <hi>proprieties,</hi> of all the people of <hi>England,</hi> by their abſolute wills and pleaſures; and to deal worſe and more arbytrary with the honeſt Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then any Conqueror that ever went before them did, although themſelves againſt the late King, have in the Kings Caſe ſtated, p. 22. by <hi>John Cook</hi> their own Atturney Gen. publikely declared, <hi>That Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest is a Title or Government fit to be exerciſed amongſt Beares and Wolves; but not in the leaſt amongſt men.</hi> And for any to aver Us in <hi>England</hi> to be a conquered Nation, is not only expreſly againſt all the tenour of the <hi>Armies</hi> many and remarkable <hi>Declarations;</hi> but it is ſuch an averment, then which, there can be none more pregnant and fruitful in Treaſon then it; as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Jo. Pym</hi> in his learned and rational printed Argument, by the ſpecial Order of the Houſe of Commons the 29 <hi>April,</hi> 1641. againſt the E. of <hi>Strafford</hi> avers. And further in pag. 6. ſaith. There are few Nations in the world that have not been conquered; &amp; NO doubt but the <hi>Conqueror</hi> may give what Laws he pleaſe to thoſe that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered; but if the ſucceeding pacts and Agreements do not limit and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166601:8"/>
reſtrain <hi>that Right, what people can be ſecure? England hath been conquered and Wales hath been conquered; and by this Reaſon will be in little better caſe then Ireland, if the King by the right of a Conqueror give lawes to his people; ſhall not the people by the ſame Reaſon be reſtored to the right of the Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to recover their liberty if they can?</hi> What can be more hurtful, more pernicious to both, then ſuch Propoſitions as theſe? Which muſt needs be moſt truly averred, have no end of bloud-ſhed and murder, and all the miſeries beſides that Tongue can expreſs, or Heart can imagine.</p>
            <p>And it is impoſſible that ever the honeſt people of England ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt, (as in ſome meaſure they have done) the General and His Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers with the Cuſtody, and preſervation of their <hi>lives, liberties, freedoms,</hi> and <hi>proprieties,</hi> with any the leaſt intentions, that when they had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued their common enemies, they ſhould ſubdue their <hi>fundamental laws and Rights</hi> (for the preſervation of which, the onely Conteſt with the common enemy was begun) and then give them a Law, flowing from their uncertain diſcretionary Wils and pleaſures. Sure I am, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and juſt <hi>David</hi> calls thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and wicked men, that would go about to deprive thoſe that ſtaid with the ſtuff, of an equall ſhare in the Conqueſt, even with thoſe that went out to fight, 1 Sam. 30.21, 22, 23, 24, 25, &amp;c. and ſure I am, that worthy man in his Age, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Pym,</hi> in his foreſaid excellent Speech, pag. 22. ſaith, <hi>That ſuch Treaſons as the ſubverſion of fundamental laws, violating of liberties, can never be good or juſtifiable by any circumſtance or occaſion; and therefore by how much the more, a truſt is upon a man, or generation of men,</hi> by ſo much the more it makes their Crime in this kind to be the more capital and haynous. Therfore, to conclude, though <hi>J. Lilburn,</hi> the priſoner at the Bar, could, and might in Law, urge many things more againſt the Parl. legalleſt power, in all manner of Acts of Attainder, the Argumenes againſt w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are excellently ſet down in that rationall &amp; highly to be commended Plea in Law, entituled, <hi>The Laws ſubverſion</hi> (p. 32.) or, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Maynards Caſe truly ſtated in</hi> 1648. by <hi>I. Houldin,</hi> Gent. and their non-juriſdiction in the leaſt, as to puniſh any man whatſoever that is not of them, for any crime whatſoever; and alſo the abſolute irrationallity and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, of their making a particular <hi>law,</hi> or their ſetting up of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Court,</hi> for a particular man; which are notably and rationally diſcuſſed upon, in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> edition of the book, entituled, <hi>The Picture of the Councel of state,</hi> p. 4, 5, 6. &amp; the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> edition of <hi>The legal fundamental li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of England revived, aſſerted, &amp; vindicated,</hi> p 71, 72, 73. yea, he might urge many Arguments, lawfully to prove, that the parl. was no parl. when they paſt the ſaid Act of baniſhment, but were long before diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166601:8"/>
and that by their own conſents, when the late parl. took upon them the exerciſe of Regality, &amp; the diſſolution of Kingſhip, and the Houſe of Lords; as is notably endeavored to be proved in the late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of ſeveral of the Armies Champions; as particularly, one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed to be printed for <hi>G. Calvert,</hi> and another by <hi>R. Moon,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in Pauls Church-yard. Yet he ſhall cloſe all at preſent with this laſt Plea, <hi>viz.</hi> That although by the ſaid unjuſt Act of baniſhment, the Act it ſelf doth authorize all <hi>Judges, Mayors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs,</hi> and all other other Officers, as well <hi>Military</hi> as <hi>Civil,</hi> in their reſpective places, to be aiding and aſſiſting in apprehending &amp;c. the ſaid baniſhed Lieu. Col. <hi>John Lilburn;</hi> yet it authorizeth none of them in the leaſt to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, try, condemn, and execute the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act; and therefore by reaſon of the inſufficiency of the ſaid Act, in that very particular, although <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> Gentleman, now priſoner at the Bar, were that Lieu. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act of baniſhment (as with confidence, for the juſt and legal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, at the beginning of this his Plea it mentioned, he doth avow he is not) yet in regard the Parliament is diſſolved, that made the ſaid Act, which in reaſon (by reaſon of the ſaid inſufficiency of the ſaid Act) cannot otherwiſe be ſuppoſed; but as they paſt the Act of baniſhment themſelves, againſt the <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> therein mentioned and meant; ſo they reſolved to reſerve only to themſelves, the final judging and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of him; which cannot be done now without their ſitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And further he avers, that its impoſſible, as things at preſent in England now ſtands, to find a legal number of men, or one ſingle legal men, to give a legal Commiſſion to any man or men in England, <hi>to hold a legal Court of Iuſtice</hi> to try <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> now priſoner at the Bar, either upon pretence for tranſgreſſing the ſaid unjuſt and illegal Act of baniſhment, or for any other real, or pretended Crime whatſoever: And, therfore, the premiſes duly and legally weighed and conſidered, he prayes, and demands, as his abſolute Right, the judgment of the Court upon the inſufficiency &amp; invalidity of proceedings now had againſt him, on the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of</hi> England's behalf, in point of Law, before he put himſelf upon the Countrey for any further Trial.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune</hi> 28. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The illegal Mittimus of the <hi>Lord Major.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHeras it was enacted by a late Act of Parl. (<hi>entituled an Act for the execution of a judgement given in Parliament, against Lieu. Col.</hi> John Lilburne) that the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> ſhould within twenty days to be accounted from the 15 <hi>day of Ianuary,</hi> 1651. depart out of <hi>England,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166601:9"/>
Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and the Iſlands, Territories and Dominions thereof; and that in caſe the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> at any time, after the expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid 20 days, to be accompted as aforeſaid, ſhould be found or ſhould be remaining within England, Scotland, Ireland, or within any of the Iſlands, Territories or Dominions thereof, <hi>the ſaid</hi> J. Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne <hi>is thereby adjudged a Felon, and to be executed as a Felon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in the ſaid Act was mentioned; And whereas the ſaid <hi>J. Lilburne,</hi> hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining and found ſince the expiration of the ſaid 20 dayes within the Liberties of the City of London, in the Commonwealth of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, contrary to the ſaid Act; Theſe are therefore in the <hi>Name of the Keepers of the Liberties</hi> of England by Authority of Parl. to will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you forthwith upon receipt hereof, to receive into your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the body of the ſaid <hi>J. Lilburne,</hi> whom I ſend unto you herewith, for the <hi>Felony aforeſaid,</hi> and him ſafely to keep, untill he ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by due courſe of Law, and this ſhall be your Warrant. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under my Hand and Seal, Dated <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 16 <hi>day of Iune,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JOHN FOWK,</hi> Major.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>To the Keepers of the Goale of Newgate.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>
               <hi>Postſcript.</hi> Reader, if thou peruſeſt the <hi>Charges</hi> or <hi>Proceedings</hi> againſt King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, or King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, or the late King <hi>Charles;</hi> or againſt the Judges, <hi>Triſillian, Fulthorp, Berknap, Cary, Holt, Burge,</hi> and <hi>Lockton,</hi> with the reſt of their Accomplices; as alſo againſt the late Ship-money Judges: Thou ſhalt clearly finde, they were all principally proceeded againſt, <hi>For ſubverting of the Peoples fundamental Laws and Liberties, and the ſetting up Arbitrarines, Will, and Pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="part">
            <p>REader, <hi>I am deſired to entreat thee take notice, that beſides all the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lilburn, <hi>and</hi> his friends, <hi>in and about the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>(the last of which of the Citizens, the</hi> Soldiers about London <hi>freely ſigned) have delivered to the Councel of State for him, which are all extant in Print; There is beſides</hi> this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, <hi>two notable Pieces in print about him; The one is entituled,</hi> A Jury-mans judgement upon the Caſe of Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn: The other is called,</hi> A Defenſive Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Lieut. Col. John Lilburne, <hi>printed and re-printed in a ſecond Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, corrected and amended the first of</hi> July, 1653. <hi>And alſo there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this day come out in print</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lilburn's <hi>Letter to the Lord Major of London, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> The Priſoners moſt mournful Cry, againſt the preſent Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Tyranny that is exerciſed upon him.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
